<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sentiment analysis on Covering Muslims</title>
    <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/categories/sentiment-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sentiment analysis on Covering Muslims</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/categories/sentiment-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Effect of Media Tone on Attitudes toward Muslims</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/polrel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/polrel/</guid>
      <description>Media coverage of Muslims has been repeatedly shown to be negative, and attitudes toward Muslims in American society are typically more negative than attitudes toward other social groups. Does the tone of media coverage directly affect public attitudes? This relationship is not well established with respect to Muslims, nor as a proposition about social groups in general. We use an online between-subjects experiment to examine whether exposure to articles of quantifiably different valences about Muslims or Catholics affects reported attitudes toward each of those groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MultiLexScaled</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/multilexscaled/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/multilexscaled/</guid>
      <description>Lexicon-based sentiment analysis, using multiple lexica and scaled against representative text corpora.   Sentiment analysis — the study of the positive or negative valence of texts — has wide-ranging applications across the social sciences. Automated approaches make it possible to code near unlimited quantities of texts with full replicability and high accuracy. Compared to machine-learning approaches, lexicon-based methods provide generalizability while sacrificing little in performance and gaining the ability to identify gradations in sentiment as well as cross-domain comparability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Report on Media Portrayals</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/annual2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/annual2020/</guid>
      <description>In this Report, we analyze 2020 coverage of six significant American racial, ethnic, or religious groups: African Americans, Asian Americans, Native Americans, Latinos, Jews, and Muslims. Latinos and African Americans are the largest of these groups, constituting approximately 19% and 13% of the US population, respectively. Asian Americans are the next most numerous, at roughly 6%. Native Americans, Jews, and Muslims each make up approximately 1-2% of the American population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Report on Media Portrayals</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/annual2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/annual2019/</guid>
      <description>In this Report, we analyze 2019 coverage of six significant American racial, ethnic, or religious groups: African Americans, Asian Americans, Native Americans, Latinos, Jews, and Muslims. Latinos and African Americans are the largest of these groups, constituting approximately 18% and 13% of the US population, respectively. Asian Americans are the next most numerous, at roughly 6%. Native Americans, Jews, and Muslims make up approximately 1-2% of the American population.
We address key questions about media coverage of these groups: Are some mentioned more frequently in US newspapers than others?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Report on Media Portrayals</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/annual2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/related/annual2018/</guid>
      <description>In this Report, we examine 2018 coverage of five significant American racial, ethnic, or religious groups: African Americans, Asian Americans, Latinos, Jews, and Muslims. Latinos and African Americans are the largest of these groups, constituting approximately 16% and 13% of the US population, respectively. Asian Americans are the next most numerous, at roughly 5%. Jews and Muslims make up much smaller proportions of the American population, at approximately 2% and 1%, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
