<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>What others have said on Covering Muslims</title>
    <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in What others have said on Covering Muslims</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Amaney A. Jamal</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/jamal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/jamal/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;This is an incredibly powerful book that convincingly illustrates that Muslims are systematically negatively portrayed in Western media. Regardless of subject matter, coverage of Muslims in several OECD countries tends to be more negative than when compared to any other group. The media in the United States, Britain, Canada, and Australia are in fact vehicles that unapologetically continue to promote Islamophobia. In an era where the roots of systemic racism are under scrutiny, it is imperative that the media take a critical inward look as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stuart Soroka</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/soroka/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/soroka/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Bleich and van der Veen offer an impressively thorough account of negativity in media coverage of Muslims. They find that Muslims receive more negative coverage than a range of other religious and ethnic groups, as farback as 1996, in the United States and across Anglo-American democracies as well. This work raises serious concerns not just for scholars of political communication and ethnic diversity, but for journalists, editors, and news consumers as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hajo G. Boomgaarden</title>
      <link>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/boomgaarden/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://covering-muslims.netlify.app/information/blurbs/boomgaarden/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;This book is a must-read for everyone interested in media and minorities. It provides a uniquely comprehensive analysis of media coverage of Muslims unseen in previous contributions on this topic. The empirical contributions presented in this book provide a benchmark for how contemporary scholarship should approach minority coverage in mass media. Conclusions are of great practical relevance for journalism practice.&amp;rdquo;
 Hajo G. Boomgaarden is Professor for Empirical Social Science Methods with a Focus on Text Analysis at the Department of Communication and currently Dean of the Faculty of Social Sciences at the University of Vienna.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
